Guide to the James Harvey Rogers Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
James Harvey Rogers papers
1904-1963
MS 421
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
31.25
(77 boxes, 1 folio)
The papers include correspondence, manuscripts, research notes, newspaper clippings, and teaching materials which document the career of James Harvey Rogers. The correspondence documents Rogers's academic appointments, research, participation in formulating economic policies for the New Deal, his post as American representative to the Economic Committee of the League of Nations, and his trip to China, Japan, and India in 1934 as a representative of the U.S. Treasury to study the silver situation. Rogers's academic life is represented by extensive notes taken during his graduate studies at Yale University (1912-1916), correspondence with members of the Economics Department (1930-1939), examinations, student papers, and material relating to Pierson College, of which he was a fellow. Rogers's research material includes offprints, clippings, press releases, and other materials on international trade, war debts, foreign investments, European economic problems, monetary reform, and the Depression. Personal papers include a small quantity of family correspondence and diaries of trips to Europe.
Rogers, James Harvey, 1886-1939
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of James H. Rogers, 1939 and 1942, and additional gifts of Byrd L. Jones and Hannah Shepperd, 1963.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, 1908-1939. II. Addresses, Essays, and Reviews, 1915-1939. III. Manuscripts and Special Projects, 1915-1963. IV. Teaching Files, 1904-1939. V. Topical Files, 1919-1940.
Scope and Contents
The James Harvey Rogers Papers are composed of correspondence, manuscripts, research notes, newspaper clippings, teaching materials, and financial papers which document Rogers's career as a professor of economics at Cornell University, the University of Missouri, and Yale University, his participation as an economic advisor to President Franklin Roosevelt, and his service as American representative to the Economic Committee of the League of Nations. Though the papers date from 1904 to 1963, the bulk of the material dates from Rogers's return to Yale as Sterling Professor of Political Economy in 1931 until his death in 1939.
The papers, which were donated to the Yale Library in 1939 and 1942 by Rogers's estate and added to in 1963 by Byrd L. Jones and Hannah Rogers Shepperd, are arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, 1908-1939; II. Addresses, Essays, and Reviews, 1915-1939; III. Manuscripts and Special Projects, 1915-1963; IV. Teaching Files, 1904-1939; V. Topical Files, 1919-1940.
About one-third of the papers is correspondence (Series I), while the rest of the papers consists of equal quantities of Rogers's own manuscripts, articles, and lectures (Series II, III, IV, and V) and of his research files and topical files, which include the writings of others, reading notes, clippings, and memorabilia for studies in economics or special assignments on government service (Series III, IV, V).
Series I contains Rogers's incoming and outgoing letters. The correspondence is predominantly professional and dated from 1908 to 1939. Letters are arranged chronologically and are selectively indexed by personal name at the end of this register.
The correspondence prior to 1921 is only fragmentary. Letters in the first three folders contain selected significant items such as letters from Rogers's teachers Vilfredo Pareto and Irving Fisher, while folders 4 - 6 concern Rogers's military service in World War I, post-war service with the Red Cross, and employment following his return to the United States.
The correspondence of the 1920s reflects Rogers's teaching duties at Cornell and the University of Missouri, his research interests, and foreign travel. In correspondence with Pareto, Fisher, Wesley Clair Mitchell, and Carl Joachim Frederich, Rogers discussed economics topics, while correspondence with Edgar Furniss during this period contains discussions of departmental politics at Yale and Cornell. Letters from former student Paul Peltason concern Rogers's speculative investments. Rogers also maintained a correspondence with former students who were employed in banking and brokerage firms in order to find positions for other students. Businessmen also supplied him with statistical data and other observations on economic trends. Carl Snyder of the Federal Reserve Board in New York was an important contact in this regard. Rogers used such information from Samuel Streit in writing Stock Speculation and the Money Market, which was published in 1927. The series also contains correspondence with Frank Taussig on the publication of this study.
In 1926 Rogers began to study economic conditions in France. The correspondence includes numerous exchanges with French bankers and government officials, while correspondence with Robert M. Haig concerns Rogers's 1927 trip to France as part of a research project centered at Columbia University. Rogers used former students August Maffrey and Robert Landman as research assistants on the study, which was published as The Process of Inflation in France, 1914-1927, and their correspondence during the period 1927 to 1929 concerns this book. There are few personal letters to describe Rogers's travels, but the 1927 correspondence reflects his excitement in being one of the first people to greet Charles Lindbergh on his landing in Paris.
The 1929 March and April correspondence concerns Rogers's dismay over the dismissal of fellow faculty member Max Meyer by the administration of the University of Missouri. Rogers voiced his concern for academic freedom again a year later in resigning from the university to accept an appointment at Yale. Negotiations concerning this appointment are contained in 1929 correspondence with Furniss. Continuing correspondence with University of Missouri colleague Harry Gunnison Brown concerns conditions there as well as the study of economics and news of former students.
The correspondence of the early 1930s demonstrates the personal effect of the Depression on Rogers and on the nature of his work in economics. Numerous friends and former students write of their economic reversals. Some correspondence also relates to Rogers's own losses on stock speculation and concern over agricultural problems affecting his farm in Society Hill, South Carolina. Rogers participated in study committees composed of other academics and business people seeking solutions to the Depression, more accurate social and economic data, and the appropriate actions of government in the crisis. This interest is reflected in correspondence with Sumner H. Slichter, the Social Science Research Council, the Twentieth Century Fund, Nicholas Murray Butler, R.M. MacIver, Arthur D. Gayer, Adolf Berle, and George Soule. Measures recommended by Rogers in America Weighs Her Gold (1931) brought him national prominence, speaking engagements, a call for advice from the new Roosevelt administration, and numerous letters from amateur monetary reformers and cranks.
The series includes correspondence with Franklin Roosevelt, Henry Morgenthau Cordell Hull, Herbert Brattner, Marvin H. McIntyre, Henry A. Wallace, Daniel C. Roper, and Herbert Feis which reflects Rogers's New Deal activities. Since Rogers and George Warren shared an office in Washington in 1933 and 1934 and could accomplish their work in person or by phone, the correspondence is not a rich source for information on Rogers's work at this time. His mission to China, Japan, and India to study the silver situation is documented and material from 1934 April to November includes cables, letters of introduction, and reports from Robert Landman and Dickson H. Leavens who accompanied Rogers on the mission. The series also contains correspondence with Jacob Viner and P. Stoppani concerning Rogers's duties as the American representative to the Economic Committee of the League of Nations.
Following his return from the Orient Rogers spent less time in Washington, and correspondence reflects the turn of his attention back to the Yale Graduate School, Pierson College, routine academic matters, continuing consultation with colleagues, the publication of two books, and study trips to Latin America. The files from 1935 on contain several exchanges with graduate students and former students including Max Millikan, Eugene and Walt Rostow, and Roger Tubby. Correspondence with Lionel D. Edie and Edward Bernays concerns prospective writing projects and speaking engagements. With Arthur Gayer and Hans Cohrssen, Rogers worked to publish a festschrift in honor of Irving Fisher, while correspondence with European colleagues Robert Marjolin and Alfred Zimmern reflects their concern for the worsening economic situation abroad. The translation of Vilfredo Pareto's Tratto di Sociologia Generalë, a project in which Rogers participated for several years, finally appeared in 1935. Details of this project can be found in the long correspondence with Andrew Bongiorno. The series also contains letters of congratulation following the 1938 appearance of Rogers's last book Capitalism in Crisis. Correspondence with Robert Landman concerns travel arrangements for trips to Colombia, Europe, and Brazil.
Throughout the series there is correspondence with longtime personal friends and family, but these letters give little insight into Rogers's personal life. Rogers's mother Florence Coker Rogers, his brothers William and John Rogers, his sisters Florence (Mrs. T. Ellison Simpson) and Hannah (Mrs. Orlando Sheppard), and cousins David and Mary Coker all write of their lives in South Carolina, but there are few letters from Rogers to his family.
Series III includes most of Rogers's speeches and articles. The series is arranged chronologically and a folder on an individual speech or article may include notes, background material, handwritten outlines and drafts, typed copies, letters of transmittal, printed copies, and summaries in the form of press releases or clippings. The series includes early student papers, Rogers's Ph.D. dissertation (folders 356-357), lectures, papers presented to professional meetings, introductions and reviews for works of others, testimony before congressional hearings, memoranda of conversations, and articles for scholarly journals and the press. Folders 383-388 contain material for Rogers's chapter "Foreign Markets and Foreign Credit" in the 1929 Report on Recent Economic Changes for the President's Conference on Unemployment. The quantity of folders from 1931 on reflects the increased demand for Rogers to speak following the publication of America Weighs Her Gold and the interest in Rogers's statements as a spokesman on New Deal economic theory. Folder titles for this period often reflect the title of a press release or news clipping whose summaries or abstracts may be the only record Rogers retained of his addresses to civic and college groups. The series also includes addresses to the Economic Committee of the League of Nations.
Series III includes both the manuscripts for each of Rogers's five books and files of material either collected or generated by Rogers in connection with a special project or assignment. For each book the files contain typed drafts and some handwritten notes. The files for The Process of Inflation in France are more extensive and also include card files of research notes, background material, and printed reviews of the book.
Special projects or assignments documented in this series include Rogers's participation, with other economists, on the Butler Commission seeking solutions to the Depression; the Rogers Mission to China, Japan, and India to study the silver situation; and Rogers's service as an economic advisor to the Roosevelt administration and American representative to the Economic Committee of the League of Nations. Most of these files include background material, memoranda by others, reports, and clippings. Occasionally there are speeches, memoranda, or reports by Rogers.
Clippings files document the increase in Rogers's public prominence after 1931. Rogers's silver study in the Orient is the most thoroughly represented special assignment. The files include Rogers's diary from his trip as well as memoranda of conversations with political leaders and economists. Dickson H. Leavens's report of the investigation in India is in folder 793. Material on the Economic Committee of the League of Nations includes committee proceedings and reports from Jacob Viner as well as Rogers's speech material. The series also includes some personal memorabilia, travel diaries from various trips to Europe, and recollections of Rogers written by former students Lester Chandler, Edwin M. Jones, and George A. Boyd. There is also a section of research material not directly related to any assignment or project.
Series IV includes lecture notes, student papers, and other materials which relate to Rogers's academic training and teaching career. The series includes the earliest material in the papers; Rogers's essays and master's thesis from the University of South Carolina are in folders 853, 857b, and 858. Most of the student lecture notes date from Rogers's course work at Yale, but folder 856 contains three notebooks from lectures by Vilfredo Pareto at the University of Geneva. Rogers's teaching notes are in boxes 63 - 65 and are arranged by course title. The Student Papers section includes papers by Rogers's students at the University of Missouri and at Yale. The papers are arranged by topic; each folder may contain papers by several students. In these folders there are papers by some of Rogers's outstanding graduate students including Walt Rostow, Max Millikan, and Willy Feuerlein. The series also includes material relating to the Economics Department at Yale, including minutes of meetings and materials relating to degree requirements and curriculum.
Series V includes a variety of material types arranged by topic. The largest quantity of material is in the section Papers by Others and the related section, Research Material, which includes writings of others organized by topic, title, or author. Some of the authors are Rogers's colleagues and friends; some papers relate to areas of Rogers's special interest and were saved as research material; and some papers were submitted to Rogers by amateur economists with their solutions to contemporary monetary problems. The series includes other types of reference material in the forms of news analyses, press releases and summaries, and clippings; photographs from Rogers's travels abroad; and a published memorial tribute by Walt Rostow and Edgar Furniss. The series concludes with a section of Writings which includes outlines, drafts, and notes for prospective, but never published, works by James Harvey Rogers.
Biographical / Historical
James Harvey Rogers studied economics with Vilfredo Pareto at the University of Geneva and received a Ph.D. from Yale University in 1916. He taught economics at Cornell University and the University of Missouri and was Sterling Professor of Political Economy at Yale from 1931 until his death in 1939. From 1933 to 1934 he was an advisor to the Roosevelt administration on fiscal policy. He also served as a special representative of the Treasury Department in the Far East (1934) and as the American member of the Economic Committee of the League of Nations (1933-1937).
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Currency question; Depressions -- 1929; Economics -- Study and teaching; Finance; Gold standard; Inflation (Finance) -- France; Silver; China -- Economic conditions -- 1912-1949; India -- Economic conditions -- 1918-1947; Japan -- Economic conditions -- 1918-1945; United States -- Politics and government -- 1933-1945; Diaries; Economists; Educators; Berle, Adolf A., Jr., 1895-1971; Bernays, Edward L., 1891-1995; Bratter, Herbert M. (Herbert Max), 1900-1976; Brown, Harry Gunnison, 1880-1975; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947; Cohrssen, Hans R. L.; Feis, Herbert, 1893-1972; Fisher, Irving, 1867-1947; Friedrich, Carl J. (Carl Joachim), 1901-1984; Furniss, Edgar S. (Edgar Stevenson), 1890-1972; Gayer, Arthur D. (Arthur David), 1903-1951; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955; Johnson, Alvin Saunders, 1874-1971; Leavens, Dickson H.; McIntyre, Marvin Hunter, 1878-1943; Meyer, Max F. (Max Friedrich), 1873-1967; Mitchell, Wesley C. (Wesley Clair), 1874-1948; Morgenthau, Henry, 1891-1967; Pareto, Vilfredo, 1848-1923; Rogers, James Harvey, 1886-1939; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Roper, Daniel C. (Daniel Calhoun), 1867-1943; Rostow, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1913-2002; Rostow, W. W. (Walt Whitman), 1916-2003; Slichter, Sumner H. (Sumner Huber), 1892-1959; Snyder, Carl, 1869-1946; Strait, Samuel, 1870-; Taussig, F. W. (Frank William), 1859-1940; Viner, Jacob, 1892-1970; Wallace, Henry A. (Henry Agard), 1888-1965; Warburg, James P. (James Paul), 1896-1969; Warren, George F. (George Frederick), 1874-1938; United States. Department of the Treasury; Cornell University -- Faculty; League of Nations. Economic Committee; University of Missouri; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of Economics; Pierson College (Yale University)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1908-1939; Series I; 9.5 linear feet (24 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in chronological order. An index to selected correspondents is provided at the end of this register.
  - 1908 - 1922 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 1-27)
  - 1922 November 16 - 1924 December 31 (Box 2, Folder 28-44)
  - 1925 January 1 - 1926 December 31 (Box 3, Folder 45-54)
  - 1927 January 1 - 1928 February 10 (Box 4, Folder 55-65)
  - 1928 February 11 - December 12 (Box 5, Folder 66-76)
  - 1928 December 13 - 1930 January 10 (Box 6, Folder 77-88)
  - 1930 January 11 - December 15 (Box 7, Folder 89-100)
  - 1930 December 16 - 1931 September 12 (Box 8, Folder 101-109)
  - 1931 September 13 - 1932 January 22 (Box 9, Folder 110-118)
  - 1932 January 23 - July 15 (Box 10, Folder 119-127)
  - 1932 July 16 - 1933 May 2 (Box 11, Folder 128-137)
  - 1933 May 3 - October 27 (Box 12, Folder 138-150)
  - 1933 October 28 - 1934 March 18 (Box 13, Folder 151-160)
  - 1934 March 19 - July 16 (Box 14, Folder 161-174)
  - 1934 July 17 - December 10 (Box 15, Folder 175-187)
  - 1934 December 10 - 1935 June 30 (Box 16, Folder 188-204)
  - 1935 July 1 - 1936 January 31 (Box 17, Folder 205-222)
  - 1936 February 1 - June 2 (Box 18, Folder 223-239)
  - 1936 June 3 - December 2 (Box 19, Folder 240-255)
  - 1936 December 3 - 1937 May 3 (Box 20, Folder 256-271)
  - 1937 May 3 - December 31 (Box 21, Folder 272-288)
  - 1938 January 1 - August 31 (Box 22, Folder 289-306)
  - 1938 September 1 - 1939 February 6 (Box 23, Folder 307-327)
  - 1939 February 7 - August 5 (Box 24, Folder 328-342)
  - Drafts of letters (Box 24, Folder 343)
  - Incomplete letters (Box 24, Folder 344)
  - Undated; A-Z (Box 24, Folder 345-353)
- ADDRESSES, ESSAYS, AND REVIEWS, 1915-1939; Series II; 2.5 linear feet (6 boxes)
  This series is arranged in chronological order. Undated materials are filed at the end of the series.
  - "Surplus Utility", 1915 (Box 25, Folder 354)
  - "Some Theorems on the Incidence of Taxes on the Production of Commodities", 1916 (Box 25, Folder 355)
  - "Some Theories on the Incidence of Taxation", 1916 (Box 25, Folder 356-357)
  - Notes and reports, Priorities Committee, Council of National Defense, 1917-1918 (Box 25, Folder 358)
  - "A Method of Determining Priority Classification", 1918 (Box 25, Folder 359)
  - Paper before Alpha Zeta Pi, 1920 (Box 25, Folder 360)
  - Address on the work of the American Red Cross, 1921 (Box 25, Folder 361)
  - "The Financial Plight of Central Europe", 1921-1922 (Box 25, Folder 362)
  - "Some Problems on Marginal and Average Cost Curves", 1922 (Box 25, Folder 363)
  - "Talk on European Trip of 1922", 1922 October (Box 25, Folder 364)
  - "Effects of Currency Depreciations", 1922 November (Box 25, Folder 365)
  - "The German Inflation Policy", 1922 November (Box 25, Folder 366)
  - Testimony in favor of a bill to stabilize purchasing power of money, 1922 December (Box 25, Folder 367)
  - "Criticism of Papers on 'Outlook for 1923'", 1922 (Box 25, Folder 368)
  - Review of "The Trust Problem in the U.S.", 1923 February (Box 25, Folder 369)
  - "The Problem of the Control of Cyclical Fluctuations in the Price Level…", 1923 June (Box 25, Folder 370)
  - "Outline of Friedrich Plan for Stable Commodity Banking", 1923 July (Box 25, Folder 371)
  - "Who is to Blame?", 1923 September (Box 25, Folder 372)
  - "A Legitimate Question", 1923 November (Box 25, Folder 373)
  - Testimony from hearings on H.R. 494, 1924 February (Box 25, Folder 374)
  - "Vilfredo Pareto: The Mathematician of the Social Sciences", 1924 August (Box 25, Folder 375)
  - Memorandum warning against a stock deal, 1924 (Box 25, Folder 376)
  - "Revolutionizing College Environment with an Honors System", 1925 August (Box 25, Folder 377)
  - Testimony, Strong Bill hearings, 1926 (Box 25, Folder 378)
  - "The Effect of Stock Speculation on the New York Money Market", 1926 May (Box 25, Folder 379)
  - Geneva lectures, 1926 August (Box 26, Folder 380)
  - Press release on French finance and government, 1927 (Box 26, Folder 381)
  - Outline of research project, 1929 (Box 26, Folder 382)
  - "Foreign Markets and Foreign Credit", 1929 (Box 26, Folder 383-388)
  - "The Position of the United States in World Affairs", 1930 May (Box 26, Folder 389)
  - "Criticism of the Papers of Professors Patterson and Donaldson", 1930 December (Box 26, Folder 390)
  - "Federal Reserve Urged to Aid Bonds by Buying Government Securities", 1931 March (Box 26, Folder 391)
  - "The Position of the U.S. in the Present World Depression", 1931 March (Box 27, Folder 392)
  - "Distributive System Fails as Decrepit Price System Slows Trend, 1931 May (Box 27, Folder 393)
  - "Professor Rogers Attacks Gold Standard and American Tariff", 1931 October (Box 27, Folder 394)
  - "Urge Federal Reserve to Initiate Steps to End Depression, 1931 October (Box 27, Folder 395)
  - Abstract of statement of James Harvey Rogers, Bankers' Club luncheon, 1931 October (Box 27, Folder 396)
  - "The ABC of the Gold Standard", 1931 October (Box 27, Folder 397)
  - "The Bank and Prosperity by Lionel D. Edie", 1931 October (Box 27, Folder 398)
  - "Gold", 1931 November (Box 27, Folder 399)
  - "World Fast Moving into a System of Trade Restrictions", 1931 December (Box 27, Folder 400)
  - Minutes of the Informal Conference of Economists of the Social Science Research Council, 1931 December (Box 27, Folder 401)
  - "The Absorption of Credit", 1931 December (Box 27, Folder 402-403)
  - "Gold, International Credits and Depression", 1931-1932 (Box 27, Folder 404)
  - "On Inflation Sentiment in Congress", 1932 January (Box 27, Folder 405)
  - "Gold, International Trade Balances, and Prosperity", 1932 January (Box 27, Folder 406)
  - "Gold and American Depression", 1932 January (Box 27, Folder 407)
  - "The Gold Standard in Relation to Foreign Policy", 1932 January-February (Box 27, Folder 408-409)
  - "The International Gold Situation;" "Gold and Depression", 1932 February (Box 27, Folder 410)
  - "Federal Reserve Policy and the Gold Standard", 1932 March (Box 27, Folder 411)
  - "The Gold Standard and the Present Crisis", 1932 March - April (Box 27, Folder 412)
  - "The New American Credit Policy in the Maintenance of the Gold Standard", 1932 April (Box 27, Folder 413)
  - "Foreign Credits and International Trade", 1932 April (Box 27, Folder 414)
  - "If I Were Financial Dictator", 1932 July (Box 28, Folder 415)
  - "Gold Problems and International Trade", 1932 August (Box 28, Folder 416)